Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos Papers, 1960-1998 and undated, bulk 1975-1991 RL.00664
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research Series, circa 1960-1996 and undated, 14 boxes
  - Clippings and Documents Subseries, circa 1960-1995 and undated
    - Moving Target, 1976-1977
      - Page proofs, notes, chapters 1-16 and afterword, undated (Box 18)
    - New demographics, 1976, 6 folders (Box 19)
      - Beyond demographics, 1984 (Box 19)
      - New demographic questions, 1984 (Box 19)
      - Understanding the New Demographics, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Over forty-nine, 1976-1991 and undated, 6 folders
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 19)
      - Media analysis, 1976-1991 (Box 19)
    - Partnership adjustments, 1977-1980 and undated (Box 20)
    - Partnership husbands, undated (Box 20)
    - Pre-Testing, undated (Box 20)
    - Professional women and men, 1993 (Box 20)
    - Sex role: stereotypes, 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Social class: husband attitudes, undated (Box 20)
    - Status of women, 1989-1994 and undated, 4 folders (Box 20)
    - Teens, 1988-1992 and undated (Box 20)
    - Trends, 1987-1995 and undated
      - Advertising trends, 1987-1995 (Box 20)
      - Australia, undated (Box 20)
      - International consumer trends, 1985-1995 (Box 20)
      - Social trends, 1985-1995 (Box 20)
    - United Nations (UN) (Box 21)
      - Women, 1974 (Box 21)
      - Women in Latin America, 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - What it means to marketers, 1976-1981 and undated, 6 folders (Box 21)
    - Why women work, 1978-1981 and undated (Box 21)
    - Women and advertising, 1978-1982, 3 folders (Box 22A)
    - Women and media, 1985-1992, 2 folders (Box 22A)
    - Women and politics, 1985-1992 (Box 22A)
    - Women and society
      - Authority figures, 1977-1980 (Box 22A)
      - Corporate, 1978-1980 (Box 22A)
      - Currently unassigned, 1977-1981 (Box 22A)
      - Future, 1977-1980 (Box 22B)
      - How they see their lives, 1980 (Box 22B)
      - Life cycle, 1977-1980 (Box 22B)
      - Media, 1980 (Box 22B)
      - Politics, 1978-1980, 2 folders (Box 22B)
    - Women at work, 1974, 3 folders (Box 22B)
    - Women entrepreneurs, 1986-1992 (Box 23)
    - Women industry, 1977-1981 (Box 23)
    - Women in:
      - Afghanistan, undated (Box 23)
      - Africa, undated (Box 23)
      - Canada, 1988-1993 (Box 23)
      - China, 1992 (Box 23)
      - Great Britain, 1976-1990 (Box 23)
      - Italy, 1987 (Box 23)
      - Ireland, 1990-1993 (Box 23)
      - Japan, 1988-1995 (Box 23)
      - Latin America, 1986-1988 (Box 23)
      - Russia, 1989 (Box 23)
      - Scandinavia, 1985-1991 (Box 23)
      - Spain, 1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's aspirations, undated (Box 23)
    - Women's City Club of New York, 1988-1993 (Box 23)
    - Women's market, 1986-1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's movement, 1985-1989 (Box 23)
    - Women's role, 1974 (Box 23)
    - Working women (Box 24)
      - Australia, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Austria, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Belgium, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Brazil, 1970s (Box 24)
      - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 24)
      - Denmark, 1974 (Box 24)
      - General, 1970s-1990s, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - International Overview, 1974 and undated (Box 24)
      - Italy, 1973-1974 (Box 24)
      - Japan, 1968-1974 (Box 24)
      - Product Use, 1970s (Box 24)
      - South Africa, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Sweden, 1974 (Box 24)
      - United Kingdom, 1974 (Box 24)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970s-1990s (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1992, 1-2 of 9 folders (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1992, 3-9 of 9 folders (Box 25)
  - Published Materials subseries, 1970s-1996 and undated
    Includes publications related to Bartos' own work, but not written by her. Arranged alphabetically.
    - 1990s and Beyond, 1990 (Box 25)
    - 1977 Yankelovich Special Report, 1977 (Box 25)
    - Advertising for Women Under 49: Six TV Commercials, 1983 (Box 25)
    - American Women in International Women's Year, 1975 (Box 25)
    - Arab as Consumer: Arab Attitudes on Trade and the Advertising Media, undated (Box 25)
    - AWNY Report
      - A Study of Women and Men in the Advertising/Communications Industry, 1993 (Box 25)
      - Press Coverage on The AWNY Report as of June 7,1993, 1993 (Box 25)
    - Cleo Three S Report on Self, Status and Sexuality, undated (Box 26)
    - Cosmopolitan Report on the Changing Life Course of American Women, (vol. 1-3), 1985-1987 (Box 26)
    - Creative Approach Test, undated (Box 26)
    - Decade of Women: A Ms. History of the Seventies in Words and Pictures, 1980 (Box 26)
    - Esquire: A Celebration of the New American Woman, 1984 (Box 26)
    - Gallup Study of Attitudes Towards Advertising, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Global Dynamics-Glass Ceiling: Perception or Reality, undated (Box 26)
    - J.D. Power and Associates 1996 Media Power Report, 1996 (Box 26)
    - Ladies Home Journal American Woman Survey, 1992 (Box 27)
    - J. Walter Thompson Reports
      - Advertising in Black America, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Advertising to Women: The Impact of Employment and Life-Style on the Media Behavior of Women, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Creative Development Program, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Crisis in Branding, 1978 (Box 27)
      - Communications Capability of J. Walter Thompson Company, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Communications Research Viewpoint on Concept Testing, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Do-It-Yourself Workbook for Developing a Moving Target Presentation, 1970s (Box 27)
      - Exploration of the Attitudes of Marine Wives Towards the Marine Wives Retention Booklet, 1973 (Box 27)
      - Special Markets Group, circa 1971 (Box 27)
    - Roper Reports Index, 1973-1986, 1986 (Box 27)
    - Virginia Slims American Women's Opinion Poll, 1980-1990 (Box 27)
    - Whirlpool Foundation Study:, 1995-1996 (Box 28)
      - Women, New Priorities, 1995 (Box 28)
      - Women, New Providers, 1996 (Box 28)
    - Woman's Place: Changing Place of Women in Britain, 1986 (Box 28)
    - Women, Work, and Markets of the 80's, 1979 (Box 28)
    - Women's Campaign Research Fund: Women Leaders for a Change, 1970s (Box 28)
    - Working Women 1980-1985: An Emerging Market, circa 1980 (Box 28)
    - Working Women, April 1972, 1972 (Box 28)
    - Working Women, Social Values Perspectives, 1980 (Box 28)
    - Working Woman Study, 1985 (Box 28)
    - Working Woman Study: Cities Edition, undated (Box 28)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1977-1990 and undated, 3 boxes
  Consists of audio and visual copies of presentations or interviews given by Bartos. Includes tape recordings of interviews from Bartos' work on The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research, promotional work and interviews, and videotaped copies of speeches given by Bartos.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restriction Note: Originals and Reference Master copies are closed to patron use. Patrons should consult Use Copies available in collection.
  - Originals (CLOSED)
    - Videocassettes (Box 29)
      - OR1. Aging Project, 1983. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR2. Rio de Janeiro, 1980. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR3. Founding Fathers of Research, undated. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR4. The Moving Target, 1977. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR5. Women Say the Darndest Things, 1983. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR6. Breakfast Speaker, 1990. VHS. (Box 29)
      - OR7. Images of Women in Advertising, 1989. VHS-M. (Box 29)
      - OR8. WPP Group Plc, undated. VHS. (Box 29)
    - Audio cassettes
      - OR9. Women Talk Business, 1990. Cassette. (Box 29)
      - OR10. Marketing to Women Around the World, 1989. Cassette. (Box 29)
  - Master copies (not for reference use)
    - Video materials (Box 30)
      Format: BetacamSP. Created: 2006.
      - MC1-MC6, MC8 (Box 30)
    - Audio materials
      Format: Audio cassette. Created: 2006.
      - MC9-MC10 (Box 30)
  - Use copies
    - Video materials (Box 31)
      Format: DVD. Created: 2006.
      - UC1-UC6, UC8 (Box 31)
    - Audio materials
      Format: Audio cassette. Created: 2006
      - UC9-UC10 (Box 31)
- 2015 Addition, 1964-2003 and undated; 1
  - Correspondence, 1964-1996; 1
    - Al Stridsberg (JWT), 1985-1992 (Box A1)
    - Apres- speech thank yous, 1964-1996 (Box A1)
    - Book/ R.B. events, 1982 (Box A1)
    - C200 Council (Consortium of businesswomen founded by Katherine Graham and Christie Hefner), 1993-1995 (Box A1)
    - Congratulatory notes, 1981-1996; 3 folders (Box A1)
    - Correspondence London, Milan, France, 1980-1987 (Box A1)
    - Correspondence with Japanese women, 1978 (Box A2)
    - Cover quotes, 1988 (Box A2)
    - Do-it-yourself/Distribution, 1981 (Box A2)
    - Eli Acimen, 1995 (Box A2)
    - Family Gap articles, 1992 (Box A2)
    - Faxes sent, 1989 (Box A2)
    - The Final Word, 1987-1988 (Box A2)
    - General correspondence, 1975-1992; 3 folders (Box A2)
    - General correspondence, 1975-1992; 5 folders (Box A3)
    - Gordon Heald (Gallup), 1986 (Box A3)
    - International corresponence, 1987-1996 (Box A3)
    - International corresponence, 1987-1996; 3 folders (Box A4)
    - Jean Arachtingi (media consultant in Europe), 1990 (Box A4)
    - John McArthur (Dean, Harvard Business School), 1984 (Box A4)
    - JWT correspondence, 1975-1994 (Box A4)
    - Lamont (Monty) Greene (Wanamaker Associates), 1992 (Box A4)
    - New York Woman, 1986 (Box A4)
    - Operations Committee, 1983 (Box A4)
    - Paul Lazarsfeld Fund, 1981-1983 (Box A4)
    - Prospects, 1983-1990 (Box A4)
    - RB Book/Congratulations, 1982 (Box A4)
    - Robert Martin (Spencer Stuart and Associates), 1978 (Box A5)
    - Seminar in Mexico, 1979 (Box A5)
    - South America correspondence, 1980 (Box A5)
    - Stephen Buck (AGB Research, London), 1988-1990 (Box A5)
    - Steven Osterweis (New York University Institute of Retail Management), 1978-1984 (Box A5)
    - Ted Wilson (JWT), 1974 (Box A5)
    - WAPOR Women's Committee (World Association for Public Opinion Research), 1989-1991; 2 folders (Box A5)
    - Women's Forum, 1992 (Box A5)
  - Marketing, 1976-1997 and undated; 2
    - Ad Forum, 1982 (Box A5)
    - Ad Week, 1982 (Box A5)
    - Ads that Irritate, 1981 (Box A5)
    - Advertising Age, 1982 (Box A5)
    - Advertising Research Foundation, 1985-1986 (Box A5)
    - Advertising Research Yesterday, Today, Tomorrow, 1986 (Box A5)
    - Aging in America: Current Trends & Future Directions, 1988 (Box A6)
    - AMA Journal of Marketing, 1977 (Box A6)
    - American Women Today and Tomorrow, 1977 (Box A6)
    - Anny, 1978 (Box A6)
    - Audience, 1981 (Box A6)
    - Bank Marketing, 1978 (Box A6)
    - Campbell Soup, 1989 (Box A6)
    - Carnegie Hill News, 1986 (Box A6)
    - Christian Science Monitor, 1978-1980 (Box A6)
    - Comprehension & Miscompression of Print Communications, 1987 (Box A6)
    - Esomar, 1989 (Box A6)
    - Exploring Mysterious Markets, 1979 (Box A6)
    - Focus Groups: Issues and approaches-ARF, 1985 (Box A6)
    - Harry O'Neil (Editor, Marketing Research), 1988-1991 (Box A6)
    - HBS Press on book Marketing to Women, undated (Box A6)
    - How Consumers over Forty-nine Respond to Advertising, undated (Box A6)
    - International Herald Tribune, 1984 (Box A6)
    - International Journal of Advertising, 1983 (Box A6)
    - Italian Youth Today, 1988 (Box A6)
    - Life Advertiser, 1976 (Box A6)
    - Marketing Communications, 1986 (Box A6)
    - Marketing Insights, 1989 (Box A6)
    - Marketing Review, 1976-1994 (Box A6)
    - Marketing Times, 1976 (Box A7)
    - Maurine Weiner Greenwald (Professor, University of Pittsburgh), essay on The Moving Target, 1997 (Box A7)
    - MORI Project: Women the New Providers (Whirlpool Foundation), 1995; 2 folders (Box A7)
    - New Demographics, undated (Box A7)
    - New Demographics Databases, 1988 (Box A7)
    - Over 49: The Invisible Market, 1980 (Box A7)
    - Photo Review, 1989 (Box A7)
    - Point of View: Bartos Responds, 1994 (Box A7)
    - Public relations, 1980-1989 (Box A7)
    - Qualitative Research ARF 50th Anniversary, 1986 (Box A7)
    - Report- Study on Image of Women in Advertising, undated (Box A7)
    - Revlon, demographics forecast, 1996 (Box A8)
    - Revue Francaise du Marketing, 1989 (Box A8)
    - Roper Center, 1989 (Box A8)
    - Schizophrenia article, undated (Box A8)
    - Talking to Women, 1995 (Box A8)
    - Target: Latin America, undated (Box A8)
    - The Travel Agent, 1982 (Box A8)
    - Valerie Free (Editor, Marketing Insights), 1991 (Box A8)
    - What Every Marketer Should Know about Women, 1978 (Box A8)
    - Women and travel, 1982 (Box A8)
    - Workin Woman Magazine, 1979 (Box A8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-2001 and undated; 3
    - Action implications from book, undated (Box A8)
    - Advertising nostalgia, 1999 (Box A8)
    - Advertising Woman of the Year, 1998 (Box A8)
    - AMA (American Marketing Association), 1986-1987 (Box A8)
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies, 1987-1988 (Box A8)
    - Anna Dehavenon (activist and homeless advocate), 1994-1998; 3 folders (Box A9)
    - Anna Dehavenon publications, 1993-1994; 2 folders (Box A9)
    - Biographies of Bartos, undated (Box A9)
    - Bob Worcester Project (MORI/Whirlpool Foundation), 1995-1996 (Box A9)
    - Butterworth Heineman (British publisher), 1989-1993 (Box A10)
    - Chapter 7: Women as Target, 1998 (Box A10)
    - Citymeals-on-Wheels the Power Lunch, 2001 (Box A10)
    - Computers/Tech, 1999 (Box A10)
    - Contracts, 1979-1993 (Box A10)
    - Deciding Vote '96, 1995 (Box A10)
    - Derived status (research), 1989; 2 folders (Box A10)
    - Diane Casper (Young/Casper Advertising), 1987-1988 (Box A10)
    - Distributed articles/speeches (digital objects), 1988 (Box A10)
    - Duke University JWT Archives, 1990 (Box A10)
    - Elayn Bernay (book collaboration proposal), 1974 (Box A11)
    - First College Graduating Class of New Millenium (Harris poll), 2001 (Box A11)
    - The Globalization of Consumer Markets Ch 9, 1991 (Box A11)
    - Health Letters, 1994-1999; 4 folders (Box A11)
    - Health Letters, 1994-1999 (Box A12)
    - Heifer Project International Wild, 2001 (Box A12)
    - Information sources, 1987 and undated (Box A12)
    - Jane Creel (Society of Consumer Affairs), 1987-1988 (Box A12)
    - Like/dislike questions, undated (Box A12)
    - Market Research Council, 1991-1992 (Box A12)
    - The Moving Target, undated (Box A12)
    - New York Office telephone directory, 1987 (Box A12)
    - Paul Lazarsfeld: Qualitative Analysis, undated (Box A12)
    - Photo prints, undated (Box A12)
    - Research quality, 1991 (Box A13)
    - Rob Worcester articles, 1989-1991 (Box A13)
    - Scrapbook, 1987 (Box A20)
    - Senior Network, 1996-1997 (Box A13)
    - Sketch, 1982 (Box A20)
    - Telefax, 1994 (Box A13)
    - Traffic Audit Bureau, 1986 (Box A13)
    - Wapor Task Force, 1990-1994 (Box A13)
    - Women's Campaign Research Fund, 1993-1995, undated (Box A13)
    - World Gold Council, 1990 (Box A13)
  - Presentations, 1973-2003 and undated; 4
    - Advertising and Consumer: New Perspectives (speech to ACA), 1977 (Box A13)
    - Advertising and Credibility, 1984-1986 (Box A13)
    - Advertising and the Economy, 1975 (Box A13)
    - Advertising: What, why, how, 1986 (Box A13)
    - ARF Financial Research Council, 1992 (Box A13)
    - Association for Consumer Research, 1990 (Box A14)
    - Auto Industry Cleveland, 1980 (Box A14)
    - Barnard Summit-Women, Leadership and the Future, 2001 (Box A14)
    - Beyond the Cookie Cutter II, 1988 (Box A14)
    - Beyond the Cookie Cutter NYC, 1982-1984 (Box A14)
    - Beyond the Rocking Chair, 1981-1988 (Box A14)
    - Bonnie Sherk (Living Library), 1987-1996 (Box A14)
    - Car Market Dearborn, 1987 (Box A14)
    - Case history (talk on agency credibility), undated (Box A14)
    - Challenge of Change, 1986-1988 (Box A14)
    - Challenging Our Assumptions About Marketplace, 1991 (Box A14)
    - Challenging Our Assumptions San Diego, 1986 (Box A14)
    - Challenging Our Assumptions Toronto, 1986 (Box A14)
    - Changes and Challenges, Wharton Conf, 1985-1986 (Box A14)
    - Changing Consumer, 1987-1989 (Box A14)
    - Changing Markets, 1983 (Box A14)
    - Changing Population Demographics, 1979 (Box A14)
    - Consumer Trends in the 80's, 1983 (Box A15)
    - Customer for Life Insurance, 1976 (Box A15)
    - Demographics of Older Shoppers 1 and 2 persons, 1982 (Box A15)
    - Do-it-yourself Workbook, undated (Box A15)
    - Do we really have to make them mad to sell?, 1980 (Box A15)
    - Eric Mafuna (Black viewpoint on U.S. business presence in South Africa), 1985 (Box A15)
    - Excellence in Advertising, 1984 (Box A15)
    - Facts of Life, 1984-1987; 3 folders (Box A15)
    - Food Commodities Promotion Symposium, 1985 (Box A15)
    - Food Marketing Institute Chicago, 1985 (Box A15)
    - Fragrance Foundation Summit 2000, 1990 (Box A15)
    - The International Moving Target, 1989 (Box A15)
    - International Women's Forum, 2002-2003 (Box A15)
    - Inventory of Speeches, 1987-1989 (Box A15)
    - Kraft Montreal, 1984 (Box A16)
    - Lecture on Women and the Law, 2001; 2 folders (Box A16)
    - Marcio Moreiro: Save the Brands!, 1992 (Box A16)
    - Marketing Financial Services to Changing Customers, 1985 (Box A16)
    - Marketing Modeling Speech, 1990 (Box A16)
    - Marketing to the Pacific Rim, 1985 (Box A16)
    - Marketing to Women Around the World, 1990 (Box A16)
    - Marketing Yourself, 1989 (Box A16)
    - Media NYC, 1976 (Box A16)
    - Meeting the Cosmetic Needs of Tomorrow, 1983 (Box A16)
    - MINTS and the Savings Target (National Association of Mutual Savings Banks), undated (Box A16)
    - Moving Markets: Trends in the 80s, 1984 (Box A16)
    - Moving Target, 1978-1989, undated (Box A16)
    - Moving Target, 1978-1989, undated; 4 folders (Box A17)
    - Newspaper Research Council, Toronto, 1990 (Box A17)
    - Opportunities and How to Capitalize, 1976 (Box A17)
    - Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market, 1986 (Box A17)
    - Peter Georgescu (Young & Rubicam): Back to School--Advertising as a Productivity Force, 1988 (Box A17)
    - Pre-1993 Speaking Arrangements, 1988-1989 (Box A17)
    - Proceedings "Welcome Speech", 1977 (Box A17)
    - Produce Marketing Association, 1986 (Box A17)
    - Qualitative Evaluation, 1983 (Box A18)
    - Qualitative Research, 1985 (Box A18)
    - RB Guide to Speeches/Articles, undated (Box A18)
    - Reaching the Young Customer, 1989 (Box A18)
    - Research, Creativity and Tunnel Vision, 1973 (Box A18)
    - Searle Sales Speech, 1979 (Box A18)
    - Segmenting for Success London, 1994 (Box A18)
    - Social Change- New Markeing Opportunities, 1981 (Box A18)
    - Social Change and the Travel Marketer, 1976 (Box A18)
    - Solving the Communications Puzzle, 1984 (Box A18)
    - Speech to Hygrade FDS Ltd Montreal, 1984 (Box A18)
    - Target is Moving- The Changing Bank Customer, 1979 (Box A18)
    - Targeting the Top, 1984 (Box A18)
    - The Untapped Goldmine, 1989 (Box A18)
    - Using Census Data, 1979 (Box A18)
    - Values and Aspirations of Women in L.A., 1991 (Box A18)
    - Wharton, 1992 (Box A18)
    - Wharton Internationl Forum, 1990 (Box A18)
    - Who pipes, whp pays, who calls the tune?, 1974 (Box A18)
    - Why full-service agency?, 1973 (Box A18)
    - Women and Cars, 1976-1977 (Box A18)
    - Women's Economic Roundatble, 1998 (Box A18)
    - Women's Forum Member Research, 2000 (Box A18)
    - Women's Place (And Yours), 1973 (Box A18)
    - Working Women: The Invisible Cosumer Travel Market, 1973 (Box A18)
  - Publications, 1982-1991 and undated; 5
    - Rena Bartos, Die Rolle der Frau als Konsumentin. Harvard Business School (German version), 1991 (Box A19)
    - Rena Bartos, Marketing to Women Around the World. Uncorrected Proof. Harvard Business School Press, 1989 (Box A19)
    - Rena Bartos. The Moving Target (signed copies). Free Press, 1982 (Box A19)
    - Rena Bartos. Marketing to Women Around the World (signed copies). Harvard Business School Press, 1989 (Box A19)
    - Rena Bartos. Marketing to Women: A Global Perspective (British version). Harvard Business School/Heinemann, 1989 (Box A19)
    - Rena Bartos and Theodore F. Dunn. Advertising and Consumers: New Perspectives. American Association of Advertising Agencies, undated (Box A19)
  - Audiovisual Materials, 1998-2002; 6
    - RL.00664-VHS-001. Market Research Council 75th Anniversary. Video-cassette, 2002 (Box A19)
    - RL.00664-VHS-002. Women's Economic Round Table's 20th Anniversary Business Enterprise Awards. Video-cassette., 1998 (Box A19)